Traditionally, dot products are
something that's introduced really early
on in a linear algebra course, typically
right at the start. So, it might seem
strange that I've pushed them back this
far in the series.
I did this because there's a standard
way to introduce the topic which
requires nothing more than a basic
understanding of vectors, but a fuller
understanding of the role that dot
products play in math can only really be
found under the light of linear
transformations.
Before that, though, let me just briefly
cover the standard way that dot products
are introduced, which I'm assuming is at
least partially review for a number of
viewers.
Numerically, if you have two vectors of
the same dimension, two lists of numbers
with the same lengths, taking their dot
product means pairing up all of the
coordinates, multiplying those pairs
together, and adding the result.
So, the vector 1 2 dotted with 3 4 would
be 1 * 3 + 2 * 4.
The vector 6 2 8 3 dotted with 1 8 5 3
would be 6 * 1 + 2 * 8 + 8 * 5 + 3 * 3.
Luckily, this computation has a really
nice geometric interpretation. To think
about the dot product between two
vectors V and W, imagine projecting W
onto the line that passes through the
origin and the tip of V.
Multiplying the length of this
projection by the length of V, you have
the dot product V.W.
Except when this projection of W is
pointing in the opposite direction from
V, that dot product will actually be
negative.
So, when two vectors are generally
pointing in the same direction, their
dot product is positive.
When they're perpendicular, meaning the
projection of one onto the other is the
zero vector, their dot product is zero.
And if they point in generally the
opposite direction, their dot product is
negative.
Now, this interpretation is weirdly
asymmetric. It treats the two vectors
very differently. So, when I first
learned this, I was surprised that order
doesn't matter.
You could instead project V onto W,
multiply the length of the projected V
by the length of W, and get the same
result.
I mean, doesn't that feel like a really
different process?
Here's the intuition for why order
doesn't matter.
If V and W happen to have the same
length, we could leverage some symmetry.
Since projecting W onto V, then
multiplying the length of that
projection by the length of V, is a
complete mirror image of projecting V
onto W, then multiplying the length of
that projection by the length of W.
Now, if you scale one of them, say V, by
some constant like two, so that they
don't have equal length, the symmetry is
broken.
But let's think through how to interpret
the dot product between this new vector,
two times V, and W.
If you think of W is getting projected
onto V, then the dot product 2V dot W
will be exactly twice the dot product V
dot W.
This is because when you scale V by two,
it doesn't change the length of the
projection of W, but it doubles the
length of the vector that you're
projecting onto.
But on the other hand, let's say you
were thinking about V getting projected
onto W.
Well, in that case, the length of the
projection is the thing that gets scaled
when we multiply V by two, but the
length of the vector that you're
projecting onto stays constant. So, the
overall effect is still to just double
the dot product. So, even though
symmetry is broken in this case, the
effect that this scaling has on the
value of the dot product is the same
under both interpretations.
There's also one other big question that
confused me when I first learned this
stuff. Why on Earth does this numerical
process of matching coordinates,
multiplying pairs, and adding them
together have anything to do with
projection?
Well, to give a satisfactory answer, and
also to do full justice to the
significance of the dot product, we need
to unearth something a little bit deeper
going on here, which often goes by the
name duality.
But before getting into that, I need to
spend some time talking about linear
transformations from multiple dimensions
to one dimension, which is just the
number line.
These are functions that take in a 2D
vector and spit out some number. But
linear transformations are of course
much more restricted than your
run-of-the-mill function with a 2D input
and a 1D output. As with transformations
in higher dimensions, like the ones I
talked about in chapter three, there are
some formal properties that make these
functions linear. But I'm going to
purposely ignore those here so as to not
distract from our end goal, and instead
focus on a certain visual property
that's equivalent to all the formal
stuff.
If you take a line of evenly spaced dots
and apply a transformation,
a linear transformation will keep those
dots evenly spaced once they land in the
output space, which is the number line.
Otherwise, if there's some line of dots
that gets unevenly spaced, then your
transformation is not linear.
As with the cases we've seen before, one
of these linear transformations is
completely determined by where it takes
i-hat and j-hat. But this time, each one
of those basis vectors just lands on a
number. So, when we record where they
land as the columns of a matrix, each of
those columns just has a single number.
This is a 1 by 2 matrix.
Let's walk through an example of what it
means to apply one of these
transformations to a vector. Let's say
you have a linear transformation that
takes I hat to 1 and J hat to -2.
To follow where a vector with
coordinates, say 4 3, ends up, think of
breaking up this vector as 4 * I hat + 3
* J hat.
A consequence of linearity is that after
the transformation, the vector will be 4
* the place where I hat lands, 1, + 3 *
the place where J hat lands, -2,
which in this case implies that it lands
on -2.
When you do this calculation purely
numerically, it's matrix-vector
multiplication.
Now, this numerical operation of
multiplying a 1x2 matrix by a vector
feels just like taking the dot product
of two vectors. Doesn't that 1x2 matrix
just look like a vector that we tipped
on its side?
In fact, we could say right now that
there's a nice association between 1x2
matrices and 2D vectors defined by
tilting the numerical representation of
a vector on its side to get the
associated matrix, or to tip the matrix
back up to get the associated vector.
Since we're just looking at numerical
expressions right now, going back and
forth between vectors and 1x2 matrices
might feel like a silly thing to do.
But this suggests something that's truly
awesome from the geometric view. There's
some kind of connection between linear
transformations that take vectors to
numbers and vectors themselves.
Let me show an example that clarifies
the significance, and which just so
happens to also answer the dot product
puzzle from earlier.
Unlearn what you have learned, and
imagine that you don't already know that
the dot product relates to projection.
What I'm going to do here is take a copy
of the number line and place it
diagonally in space somehow, with the
number zero sitting at the origin.
Now, think of the two-dimensional unit
vector whose tip sits where the number
one on the number line is. I want to
give that guy a name, u hat.
This little guy plays an important role
in what's about to happen, so just keep
him in the back of your mind.
If we project 2D vectors straight onto
this diagonal number line, in effect,
we've just defined a function that takes
2D vectors to numbers.
What's more, this function is actually
linear since it passes our visual test
that any line of evenly spaced dots
remains evenly spaced once it lands on
the number line.
Just to be clear, even though I've
embedded the number line in 2D space
like this, the outputs of the function
are numbers, not 2D vectors.
You should think of a function that
takes in two coordinates and outputs a
single coordinate.
But that vector u hat is a
two-dimensional vector living in the
input space. It's just situated in such
a way that overlaps with the embedding
of the number line.
With this projection, we just defined a
linear transformation from 2D vectors to
numbers. So, we're going to be able to
find some kind of 1 by 2 matrix that
describes that transformation.
To find that 1 by 2 matrix, let's zoom
in on this diagonal number line setup
and think about where i hat and j hat
each land since those landing spots are
going to be the columns of the matrix.
This part's super cool. We can reason
through it with a really elegant piece
of symmetry. Since i hat and u hat are
both unit vectors, projecting i hat onto
the line passing through u hat looks
totally symmetric to projecting u hat
onto the x-axis.
So, when we ask what number does i hat
land on when it gets projected, the
answer's going to be the same as
whatever u hat lands on when it's
projected onto the x-axis.
But projecting u hat onto the x-axis
just means taking the x-coordinate of u
hat. So, by symmetry, the number where i
hat lands when it's projected onto that
diagonal number line is going to be the
x-coordinate of u hat. Isn't that cool?
The reasoning is almost identical for
the j hat case. Think about it for a
moment.
For all the same reasons, the y
coordinate of u hat gives us the number
where j hat lands when it's projected
onto the number line copy.
Pause and ponder that for a moment. I
just think that's really cool.
So, the entries of the 1 by 2 matrix
describing the projection transformation
are going to be the coordinates of u
hat.
And computing this projection
transformation for arbitrary vectors in
space, which requires multiplying that
matrix by those vectors, is
computationally identical to taking a
dot product with u hat.
This is why taking the dot product with
a unit vector can be interpreted as
projecting a vector onto the span of
that unit vector and taking the length.
So, what about non-unit vectors? For
example, let's say we take that unit
vector u hat, but we scale it up by a
factor of three.
Numerically, each of its components gets
multiplied by three. So, looking at the
matrix associated with that vector, it
takes i hat and j hat to three times the
values where they landed before.
Since this is all linear, it implies
more generally that the new matrix can
be interpreted as projecting any vector
onto the number line copy and
multiplying where it lands by three.
This is why the dot product with a
non-unit vector can be interpreted as
first projecting onto that vector, then
scaling up the length of that projection
by the length of the vector.
Take a moment to think about what
happened here. We had a linear
transformation from 2D space to the
number line, which was not defined in
terms of numerical vectors or numerical
dot products. It was just defined by
projecting space onto a diagonal copy of
the number line.
But because the transformation is
linear, it was necessarily described by
some 1 by 2 matrix. And since
multiplying a 1 by 2 matrix by a 2D
vector is the same as turning that
matrix on its side and taking a dot
product, this transformation was
inescapably related to some 2D vector.
The lesson here is that anytime you have
one of these linear transformations
whose output space is the number line,
no matter how it was defined, there's
going to be some unique vector V
corresponding to that transformation in
the sense that applying the
transformation is the same thing as
taking a dot product with that vector.
To me, this is utterly beautiful.
It's an example of something in math
called duality.
Duality shows up in many different ways
and forms throughout math, and it's
super tricky to actually define. Loosely
speaking, it refers to situations where
you have a natural but surprising
correspondence between two types of
mathematical thing.
For the linear algebra case that you
just learned about, you'd say that the
dual of a vector is the linear
transformation that it encodes.
And the dual of a linear transformation
from some space to one dimension is a
certain vector in that space.
So, to sum up, on the surface, the dot
product is a very useful geometric tool
for understanding projections and for
testing whether or not vectors tend to
point in the same direction. And that's
probably the most important thing for
you to remember about the dot product.
But, at a deeper level, dotting two
vectors together is a way to translate
one of them into the world of
transformations.
Again, numerically, this might feel like
a silly point to emphasize. It's just
two computations that happen to look
similar. But, the reason I find this so
important is that throughout math, when
you're dealing with a vector, once you
really get to know its personality,
sometimes you realize that it's easier
to understand it not as an arrow in
space, but as the physical embodiment of
a linear transformation. It's as if the
vector is really just a conceptual
shorthand for a certain transformation,
since it's easier for us to think about
arrows in space rather than moving all
of that space to the number line.
In the next video, you'll see another
really cool example of this duality in
action as I talk about the cross
product.